A Guide to the Edith Moore Sprouse Papers, 1960-2003
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Edith Moore Sprouse Papers 1960-2003
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
313
17 boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Edith Moore Sprouse.
Biographical/Historical Information
Born in Scranton, Pennsylvania, Edith Moore Kynor Sprouse (1923-2004) was a local historian, author, and preservationist. A graduate of Wellesley College, she worked briefly for the Army Map Service before discovering her true love, Northern Virginia history. Beginning in 1961, Sprouse wrote numerous books and articles about local history and undertook what she regarded as her most important project, indexing and cataloging Fairfax County government records from the 1700s through 1979. Instrumental in founding the Fairfax County Historical Commission, Sprouse served on the board of the Franconia Museum and advised the Friends of Historic Huntley. She was a member of the Northern Virginia Association for History, the Alexandria Historical Society, the Northern Virginia Chapter of the Archaeological Society of Virginia, the Friends of Gunston Hall, Historic Dumfries, and the Alexandria Public Library.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of correspondence, research materials, including computer discs and card files, and printed local history publications written and collected by Mrs. Sprouse. Of particular interest are the card files, containing extensive information on Alexandria, Fairfax, and the surrounding areas extracted from newspapers and public records as well as collected through interviews and fieldwork.
Arrangement
The correspondence and local history materials are organized chronologically; the computer discs alphabetically; the special projects and card files chronologically and by topic. The collection is divided into six series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Special Projects
Series III: Research Materials
Series IV: Computer Discs
Series V: Card Files
Series VI: Local History
Index Terms
History--Virginia--Alexandria; History--Virginia--Fairfax County; Sprouse, Edith Moore
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1960-2003 (Box 313-313A)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box-folder 313:1)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box-folder 313:2)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box-folder 313:3)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box-folder 313:4)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box-folder 313:5)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box-folder 313:6)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box-folder 313:7)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box-folder 313:8)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box-folder 313:9)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box-folder 313:10)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box-folder 313:11)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box-folder 313:12)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box-folder 313:13)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box-folder 313:14)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box-folder 313:15)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box-folder 313:16)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box-folder 313:17)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box-folder 313:18)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box-folder 313:19)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box-folder 313:20)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box-folder 313:21)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box-folder 313:22)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box-folder 313:23)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box-folder 313:24)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box-folder 313A:1)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 313A:2)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box-folder 313A:3)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box-folder 313A:4)
  - Correspondence, 1988 (Box-folder 313A:5)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box-folder 313A:6)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box-folder 313A:7)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box-folder 313A:8)
  - Correspondence, 1992 (Box-folder 313A:9)
  - Correspondence, 1993 (Box-folder 313A:10)
  - Correspondence, 1994 (Box-folder 313A:11)
  - Correspondence, 1995 (Box-folder 313A:12)
  - Correspondence, 1996 (Box-folder 313A:13)
  - Correspondence, 1997 (Box-folder 313A:14)
  - Correspondence, 1998 (Box-folder 313A:15)
  - Correspondence, 1999 (Box-folder 313A:16)
  - Correspondence, 2000 (Box-folder 313A:17)
  - Correspondence, 2001 (Box-folder 313A:18)
  - Correspondence, 2002 (Box-folder 313A:19)
  - Correspondence, 2003 (Box-folder 313A:20)
  - Correspondence with T. Triplett Russell, 1968-1978 (Box-folder 313A:21)
  - Correspondence with T. Triplett Russell, 1968-1978 (Box-folder 313A:22)
- Special Projects (Box 313B)
  - Harry Piper Letters (copies), 1767-1769 (Box-folder 313B:1)
  - Harry Piper Letters (copies), 1770-1771 (Box-folder 313B:2)
  - Harry Piper Letters (copies), 1772-1773 (Box-folder 313B:3)
  - Harry Piper Letters (copies), 1774-1775 (Box-folder 313B:4)
  - Correspondence Re: publication of Harry Piper Letters (Box-folder 313B:5)
  - Models for publication of Harry Piper Letters (Box-folder 313B:6)
  - Bicentennial Indexing Project (Box-folder 313B:7)
  - Bicentennial Indexing Project Financials (Box-folder 313B:8)
  - George Washington's 250th Anniversary Celebration (Box-folder 313B:9)
- Research Materials (Box 313C-313D)
  - War of 1812 Muster Roll 60th Regiment, Virginia Militia (Box-folder 313C:1)
  - War of 1812 Pensions, A-H (Box-folder 313C:2)
  - War of 1812 Pensions, I-R (Box-folder 313C:3)
  - War of 1812 Pensions, S-Z (Box-folder 313C:4)
  - Early 18th Century Fairfax County Revolutionary War Depositions, 1-3 (Box-folder 313C:5)
  - Early 18th Century Fairfax County Revolutionary War Depositions, 4-5 (Box-folder 313C:6)
  - Early 18th Century Fairfax County Revolutionary War Depositions (Box-folder 313C:7)
  - List of Servants and Masters, Appendix I (Box-folder 313C:8)
  - List of Servants and Masters, Appendix II (Box-folder 313C:9)
  - List of Servants and Masters, Appendix III (Box-folder 313C:10)
  - Mss. Diary Ferdinando Fairfax (Box-folder 313D:1)
  - Pedigree for the Fairfax Family of Yorkshire and Virginia (Box-folder 313D:2)
  - Stabler-Leadbeater Inventory (Box-folder 313D:3)
  - "Records of Christ Church, Alexandria, Virginia," Genealogical and History Magazine of the South, 1985 (Box-folder 313D:4)
  - Proceedings of the Commission Relating to State Prisoners 1862, Index and pp. 1-96 (Box-folder 313D:5)
  - Proceedings of the Commission Relating to State Prisoners 1862, pp. 98-152 (Box-folder 313D:6)
  - Proceedings of the Commission Relating to State Prisoners 1862, pp. 98-152 (Box-folder 313D:7)
  - Books in EMS Library (Box-folder 313D:8)
- Computer Discs (Box 313E)
  - Fairfax County in 1860, A Collective Biography (17 discs) (Box-folder 313E)
  - Fairfax News abstracts, 1843-1851, 1852, 1856, 1860 (5 discs) (Box-folder 313E)
  - 1815 Tax Table (1 disc) (Box-folder 313E)
- Card Files (Box 313F-313N)
  - War of 1812 Pension Abstracts for Alexandria and Fairfax Counties (Box 313F)
  - Subject card files on Alexandria, Fairfax, and surrounding environs, A-C (Box 313G)
  - Subject card files on Alexandria, Fairfax, and surrounding environs, D-H (Box 313H)
  - Subject card files on Alexandria, Fairfax, and surrounding environs, I-M (Box 313I)
  - Subject card files on Alexandria, Fairfax, and surrounding environs, N-S (Box 313J)
  - Subject card files on Alexandria, Fairfax, and surrounding environs, T-X (Box 313K)
  - Chronological card abstracts of Alexandria Gazette, 1784-1850 (Box 313L)
  - Chronological card abstracts of Alexandria Gazette, 1855-1900 (Box 313M)
  - Subject card abstracts of local newspapers (Box 313N)
- Local History (Box 313P)
  - Minutes of Various Northern Virginia Historical Organizations (Box-folder 313P:1)
  - Minutes of Northern Virginia Association for History Annual Meetings, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 313P:2)
  - Pioneer Society, Echoes of History,1970-1971 (Box-folder 313P:3)
  - Pioneer Society, Echoes of History,1972-1973 (Box-folder 313P:4)
  - Pioneer Society, Echoes of History,1974-1976 (Box-folder 313P:5)
  - Northern Virginia Historical Association, The Courier of Historical Events, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 313P:6)
  - Northern Virginia Historical Association, The Courier of Historical Events, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 313P:7)
  - Northern Virginia Historical Association, The Courier of Historical Events, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 313P:8)
  - Northern Virginia Historical Association, The Courier of Historical Events, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 313P:9)
  - Northern Virginia Historical Association, The Courier of Historical Events, 1994-1998 (Box-folder 313P:10)
  - Northern Virginia Historical Association, The Courier of Historical Events, 1999-2003 (Box-folder 313P:11)
  - Miscellaneous Publications (Box-folder 313P:12)
  - Miscellaneous Publications (Box-folder 313P:13)